Guide to the Phillips F. and Ruth A. Greene Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Phillips F. and Ruth A. Greene papers
1923-1977
MS 797
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(5 boxes)
The principal figures in these papers are Phillips Foster Greene, a physician and missionary, and his wife, Ruth Altman Greene, a teacher and writer who accompanied her husband during his service of nearly twenty years at the Yale-in-China Medical School in Changsha (1921-1943) and seven years in Rangoon (1951-1958). The papers consist largely of correspondence with family in the United States and with Yale-in-China staff members. The letters are important sources of information on social conditions in China and political events, as well as a record of the Greenes' day-to-day activities. Also in the papers are financial records, newspaper clippings, copies of their articles on life at Changsha, and photographs.
Greene, Phillips Foster, 1892-1967
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
A portion of the material was separated from the records of the Yale-in-China Association's New Haven office in 1977. The remainder of the papers were donated to the Yale University Library by Ruth Altman Greene in July, 1977.
Scope and Contents
The Phillips and Ruth Greene Papers are composed principally of their letters to family, friends and Yale-in-China Association colleagues written during their years of residency at Changsha, Hunan. Phillips Greene was a faculty member and surgeon at the Hsiang-Ya Medical School and hospital in Changsha (1923-1927, 1931-1941) and Director of the American Red Cross in China (1942-1943).
The papers are arranged in three series: I. Phillips Foster Greene Correspondence. II. Ruth Altmen Greene Correspondence. III. Subject Files, Writings, Photographs.
Series I (1923-1954) contains Greene's letters to his family and to the Yale-in-China staff. Subjects discussed in the correspondence include social conditions and political events in Changsha and Hunan Province; Greene's medical practice; and-Yale-in-China administrative matters. Included in Series I is a section of the correspondence of other members of Greene's family.
Series II contains Ruth Greene's correspondence with her family and Yale-in-China staff members (1923-1943), many of which were published in her account of life at Changsha, in the Hsiang-Ya-Journal. Subjects discussed include social conditions, political events and the Greenes' day-to-day activities.
Series III is composed of newspaper clippings containing biographical material on the Greenes, financial records from their period of residence at Changsha, copies of their articles describing life at Changsha and conditions in Hunan (1923-1943) and photographs.
The material in Series I was separated from the records of the Yale-in-China Association's New Haven office in 1977. The material in Series II and III was donated to the Yale University Library by Ruth Altman Greene in July 1977. The Phillips and Ruth Greene Papers are part of the Yale-China Collection.
Biographical / Historical
Phillips Greene, physician and missionary, received his B.A. from Amherst College in 1915, and his M.D. from Harvard Medical School in 1919. He was a member of the teaching staff of Hsiang-Ya (Hunan-Yale) Medical School, Changsha, China from 1923-1927; assistant professor of surgery, University of Wisconsin Medical School, 1927-1931; head of the department of surgery and dean of Hsiang-Ya Medical School, 1931-1941; clinical professor of surgery and associate dean, Long Island College of Medicine, 1944-1951; and a staff member of the Rangoon, Burma General Hospital and Medical School, 1951-1958. Greene returned to the United States in 1958 and practiced medicine in New Richmond, Ohio until 1967.
CHRONOLOGY: Phillips Foster Greene
1892 Born in Van, Turkey, son of missionaries Sarah Foster and Frederick Davis Greene.
1915 B.A., Amherst College.
1919 M.D., Harvard Medical School.
1919-1921 House Officer, General Surgery, St. Luke's Hospital and St. Mary's Children's Hospital, New York City.
1920 Married to Ruth Peabody Altman.
1923-1923 Under appointment with the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions for medical work in Turkey. Prevented from serving by political conditions, transferred to Yale-in-China at Changsha, Hunan.
1923-1927 Teaching staff of Hsiang-Ya (Hunan-Yale) Medical School, Changsha.
1927 Civil war in China, evacuated with family to United States.
1927-1931 Assistant Professor of Surgery, University of Wisconsin School of Medicine.
1931-1941 Head of Department of Surgery and Dean of Hsiang-Ya Medical school.
1942-1943 Director of the American Red Cross in China, responsible for getting supplies into China (Chungking) and distributing them to Nationalist and Communist forces.
1944-1951 Clinical Professor of Surgery and Associate Dean, Long Island College of Medicine, Brook1yn, New York.
1951-1953 Appointed to the Rangoon, Burma, General Hospital and Medical School under the United States Government Point Four Program.
1953-1958 After termination of all official United States Aid to Burma, continued to work with Rangoon Hospital and Medical School under a Rockefeller Foundation grant.
1958-1967 Returned to United States and practiced medicine in New Richmond, Ohio, until his death on 11 April 1967.
CHRONOLOGY: Ruth Altman Greene
1896 Born in Cincinnati, Ohio, daughter of Flavella Light and Daniel Lee Altman, Methodist minister.
1918 B.A., Wellesley College.
1920 Married to Phillips Foster Greene.
1921-1923 Under appointment with the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in Constantinople, Turkey.
1923-1927 In Changsha, Hunan. Evacuated in January 1927.
1927-1931 In Madison, Wisconsin. Writing and speaking on China and working with foreign students in YWCA.
1931-1936 Returned to Changsha with four children. Taught English to Hsiang-Ya students and did extensive entertaining of Chinese officials and foreign vistors from the League of Nations.
1937-1940 After a furlough in New Haven returned to Changsha at outbreak of the Sino-Japanese War. Evacuated with children in December 1937 to Philippines; later to Shanghai. In 1940 accompanied husband on trip to Kweiyang, site of Hsiang-Ya Medical School's war-time teaching. In June left for United States with children.
1940-1948 Lived in Upper Montclair, New Jersey. Helped organize the China Institute of New Jersey to train public school teachers in the history and culture of China.
1948-1949 Worked with China Institute in America on behalf of Chinese students; served on Wellesley-Yenching College Board.
1951-1958 Lived in Rangoon, Burma. Main activities were entertaining vistors, colleagues and friends; collecting material on the history and culture of Burma for use in United States schools and clubs and briefings of new State Department officials.
1958- Living in New Richmond, Ohio.
1977 Publication of Hsiang-Ya Journal based on letters written from China between 1923-1943.
various Children: Ellen Greene, Anne Greene Judy, Frederick D. Greene II, Margaret Greene Dickson.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series: I. Phillips Foster Greene Correspondence. II. Ruth Altmen Greene Correspondence. III. Subject Files, Writings, Photographs.
Medicine; Missionaries' spouses; Missions -- China; Asia; Changsha Shi (China); China -- History -- Republic, 1912-1949; China -- Politics and government; China -- Social life and customs; Rangoon (Burma); Authors; Educators; Missionaries; Physicians; Agard, Walter R. (Walter Raymond), 1894-1978; Bedell, Frances; Bevis, Palmer; Burny, Paul S.; Campbell, Edward F., Jr. (Edward Fay), 1932-; Chang, Hsiao-Chʻien, fl. 1905; Dayton, Arthur Bliss, 1889-; Dowd, Rachel A.; Greene, Phillips Foster, 1892-1967; Greene, Ruth Altman, 1896-; Hsiao, Y. T.; Hume, Edward H. (Edward Hicks), 1876-1957; Hutchins, Francis S. (Francis Stephenson), 1902-; Latourette, Kenneth Scott, 1884-1968; Smith, Robert Ashton, 1914-; Song, Qingling, 1893-1981; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-1958; Vaill, George; Weigle, Luther A. (Luther Allan), 1880-1976; Hunan-Yale College of Medicine. Hsiang-Ya Hospital (Changsha, China); Yale-China Association
- PHILLIPS FOSTER GREENE CORRESPONDENCE, 1923-1943 [1923-1959]; Series I; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I is subdivided into three sections: 1. Phillips Foster Greene Correspondence with family; 2. Phillips Foster Greene Correspondence with-Yale-in-China staff; 3. Correspondence of Greene family members.
  Series I is subdivided into three sections: I. Phillips Foster Greene Correspondence with family; II. Phillips Foster Greene Correspondence with-Yale-in-China staff; III. Correspondence of Greene family members.
  - Phillips Foster Greene Correspondence with family
    - 1923 January - 1943 December (Box 1, Folder 1-34)
  - Phillips Foster Greene Correspondence With Yale-in-China staff
    - Agard, W.R., 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Allen, Richard F., 1942 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - American Cystoscope Makers, Inc., 1944 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Arnold, Lauren, 1933-1938 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Barton, James L., 1923 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Bevis, Palmer, 1927-1930 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Bradford, Jessie R., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Brophy, John R., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Burny, Paul S., 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Campbell, E. Fay, 1930-1932 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Chang, Fu-liang, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Chang, H.C., 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Curran, J.A., 1945 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Dayton, Arthur Bliss, 1930-1967 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Dowd, Rachel A., 1923-1953 (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
    - Eastman, L.R., 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - First National Bank, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Form letters to friends, 1932-1958 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Fulton, Brank, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Goff, W.E., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Granat, Henry, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Griesback, Catharine, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Gunn, Selskar M., 1933 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Harvey, Samuel C., 1935-1944 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Hsiao, Y.T., 1939-1946 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Hume, Edward H., 1923-1941 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Hutchins, Francis S., 1928-1939 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Latourette, Kenneth S., 1928-1945 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Lobenstine, Edwin C., 1936-1945 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Luig Hsi-Fong, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - McCoy, H.L., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Millamow, F.X., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Mooreland, Kenneth, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Mass, Leslie B., 1937 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Murphy, Frederick T., 1923-1937 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - National Board of Medical Examiners, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - New England Mutual Life Insurance Co., 1931-1939 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Pearce, Agnes, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Perkins, Troy L., 1940 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Pettus, Winston, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Pi Tseng-hai, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Riggs, Ernest W., 1923 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Rinden, Arthur O., 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Rugh, Dwight, 1940-1951 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Smith, Clarence A., 1937 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Smith, Robert Ashton, 1938-1943 (Box 3, Folder 81-84)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Sun Yat-Sen (Madame), 1942 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Torrey, Emily R., 1936 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Torrey, John P., 1936 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Vaill, George D., 1954-1959 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Wakeman, Alfred J., 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Wang, K.Y., 1935 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Weigle, Luther A., 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Weigle, Richard D., 1933-1938 (Box 3, Folder 93-94)
    - Wheeler, Reginald W., 1948 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Wilson, Louise Farnam, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Yale-in-China Association, 1923-1945 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Unsigned correspondence, 1923-1945 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Correspondence of Greene family members
    - Greene, Charlotte D., 1940 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Greene, Faith, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Greene, Frederick D., 1923-1951 (Box 3, Folder 101-104)
    - Greene, Joseph K., 1939-1941 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - Greene, Lois, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - Greene children, 1932-1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 107)
- RUTH ALTMAN GREENE CORRESPONDENCE, 1923-1943 [1923-1964]; Series II; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series II is subdivided into two sections: 1. Correspondence with family; 2. Correspondence with Yale-in-China staff members.
  - Ruth Altman Greene Correspondence with family
    - 1923 January - 1943 December (Box 4, Folder 108-133)
  - Ruth Altman Greene Correspondence with Yale-in-China staff
    - Bedell, Frances, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Bentley, Elizabeth, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Bevis, Palmer, 1926-1938 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Campbell, [?], 1932 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Dayton, Arthur Bliss, 1941-1968 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Dowd, Rachel A., 1928-1945 (Box 5, Folder 139-143)
    - Hsiang-Ya Hospital personnel, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - Hutchins, Frank, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Leete, Anna W., 1936 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Lung, Y.Y., 1936 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Pritchett, Beatrice Page, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Rinden, Arthur O., 1944 (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Smith, Robert Ashton, 1938-1943 (Box 5, Folder 149-152)
    - Weigle, Richard D., 1934-1938 (Box 5, Folder 153-155)
    - Wilkinson, Maria Victoria, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 156)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence of others, 1927-1964 (Box 5, Folder 157)
    - Unidentified signatures (Box 5, Folder 158)
- SUBJECT FILES, WRITINGS, PHOTOGRAPHS, 1923-1943 [1923-1977]; Series III; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Series III is subdivided into four sections: 1. Subject files; 2. Writings of Phillips F. Greene; 3. Writings of Ruth A. Greene; 4. Photographs.
  - Subject files
    - Biographical sketches and clippings (Box 5, Folder 159)
    - Biographical clippings (Box 5, Folder 160)
    - Changsha International Relief Committee: report, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 161)
    - Financial records, 1923-1946, undated (Box 5, Folder 162-165)
    - Health reports, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 166)
    - Hsiang-Ya Hospital and College reports, 1939-1946 (Box 5, Folder 167)
    - Mailing lists (Box 5, Folder 168)
    - Meeting notes and agenda, 1933-1944 (Box 5, Folder 169)
    - Miscellaneous notes and printed matter (Box 5, Folder 170)
    - Chinese newspapers, 1932, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 171)
    - Memoranda on Chiang Kai-shik's state of China speech, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 172)
  - Writings of Phillips F. Greene
    - Letter to New York Times, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 173)
    - "What's Singing", 1944 (Box 5, Folder 173)
    - "Medical Trends in China", 1945 (Box 5, Folder 173)
    - "Experiences in Anesthesia in China", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 174)
    - "Native Medical Practices in China", undated (Box 5, Folder 174)
  - Writings of Ruth Altman Greene
    - Diary of inland China trip, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - "Fragments from a Chinese Journal", 1941 (Box 6, Folder 176)
    - "Chinese Women and War", 1944 (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - "From a Chinese Dug-Out", undated (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - "War-Time Hsiang-Ya", undated (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - "Broken Jade", undated (Box 6, Folder 178)
    - Hsiang-Ya Journal, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 179)
    - Hsiang-Ya Journal research notes (Box 6, Folder 180)
  - Photographs
    - Phillips and Ruth Greene (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - 48 photographs collected by Phillips Greene during the Sino-Japanese War, 1937-1945 (Box 7, Folder 182)